Alice Fordyce Papers, 1967-1991
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Alice Fordyce papers
1967-1991
Fordyce, Alice, d. 1993
MS 272
3 boxes (1.5 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Foundation executive; Philanthropist; Public relations specialist. Papers include personal correspondence, organization records, speeches, and an interview. The collection focuses on Fordyce's volunteer and philanthropic work with the Albert and Mary Lasker Foundation, the American Cancer Society, the National Organization for Rare Disorders, and others.
Alice Woodard Fordyce was born in Watertown, Wisconsin in 1905. She was the sister of Mary Lasker and graduated from Smith College in 1928 after spending her junior year in France studying at the University of Grenoble and the Sorbonne. She married architect Allmon Grant Fordyce in 1939 and they had one son, James Woodard Fordyce. Alice Fordyce's first job after graduating was as Assistant Director of Fashion Publicity at Lord and Taylor. In 1933 she became Assistant Director of Public Relations for the Rockefeller Center, a position she would hold until 1940. Fordyce was additionally involved in a number of medical and social organizations. She was Executive Vice President of the Albert and Mary Lasker Foundation and organized the annual Albert Lasker Medical Research Awards. She also served on a number of advisory boards and committees such as the information committee of the American Cancer Society, the National Organization for Rare Diseases as well as committees for the New York Health and Planning Advisory Committee, the National Council on Drugs and the American Museum in Britain. Fordyce was also a high-ranking member of the National Association for the Southern Poor and the American Impact Foundation. She was a founding member of the National Museum for Women in the Arts. Alice Fordyce died in 1992 in New York City.
The Alice Fordyce Papers include personal correspondence, organization records, speeches, and an audio recording of an interview conducted by Sophia Smith Collection Director Susan Grigg in 1991. The collection focuses primarily on Fordyce's volunteer work and membership in such organizations as The American Museum in Britain, the Albert and Mary Lasker Foundation, the American Cancer Society, the National Organization for Rare Disorders, the National Museum of Women in the Arts, the National Association for Southern Poor, the John E. Fogarty International Center Advisory Board, and the American Impact Center. Files for these organizations include general mailings, direct correspondence, mailing lists, fiscal reports, press releases and clippings. There are also files pertaining to Dr. Robert Newman of the Beth Israel Medical Center and methadone treatment, as well as a file on an exchange trip between U.S. and Chinese scientists in 1977.
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection.
This collection has not been fully processed and therefore may be difficult to use.
History of the Collection
Alice Fordyce donated her Papers to the Sophia Smith Collection in 1991.
Search Terms
Fordyce, Alice, 1905-1992; Albert and Mary Lasker Foundation; American Cancer Society -- History -- Sources; Drug addiction -- Treatment; Newman, Robert G.; Public relations -- Social service -- United States -- History -- Sources; Women philanthropists -- United States -- Biography -- Sources; Women executives -- United States -- Biography -- Sources
- Biographical Material
  - Resume, clippings, short biography undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Interview with Susan Grigg: two audio cassette tapes and transcript 1991 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Personal correspondence 1984-89 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Speeches by and about Fordyce 1967-90 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Organizations
  - American Cancer Society 1976-89 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - ACS's exchange trip to China 1977 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - American Impact Foundation 1984-89 (Box 1, Folder 7-8)
  - American Museum in Britain 1972-90 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Eyebank for Sight Restoration 1986-90 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - John E. Fogerty International Center Advisory Board 1985-90 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Miscellaneous committee affiliations
    - New York State Health Planning Advisory Council 1970 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - National Council on Drugs 1982
      - ICCR press releases 1991 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - National Association for the Southern Poor 1988-90 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - National Museum of Women in the Arts 1983-90 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Billie Holladay: correspondence and clippings 1983-90 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - New York State Council on Mental Hygiene Planning 1976-78 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - NORD Research Advisory Council 1986-88 (Box 2, Folder 18-19)
    - NORD Research Advisory Council 1989 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Royal Society of Medicine undated (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Beth Israel Hospital (methadone clinic) and Robert Newman
    - Correspondence and clippings 1988-89 (Box 3, Folder 22-23)
    - Methadone treatment: clippings and list of clinics 1987-88 (Box 3, Folder 24)